<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science on Abhijit&#39;s DataWorld</title>
    <link>/tags/data-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Science on Abhijit&#39;s DataWorld</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Abhijit Dasgupta</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/data-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Practical Data Science Cookbook</title>
      <link>/post/practical-data-science-cookbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/practical-data-science-cookbook/</guid>
      <description>Practical Data Science Cookbook My friends Sean Murphy, Ben Bengfort, Tony Ojeda and I recently published a book, Practical Data Science Cookbook. All of us are heavily involved in developing the data community in the Washington DC metro area, serving on the Board of Directors of Data Community DC. Sean and Ben co-organize the meetup Data Innovation DC and I co-organize the meetup Statistical Programming DC.
Our intention in writing this book is to provide the data practitioner some guidance about how to navigate the data science pipeline, from data acquisition to final reports and data applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The many faces of statistics/data science: Can&#39;t we all just get along and learn from each other?</title>
      <link>/post/the-many-faces-of-statisticsdata-science-cant-we-all-just-get-along-and-learn-from-each-other/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-many-faces-of-statisticsdata-science-cant-we-all-just-get-along-and-learn-from-each-other/</guid>
      <description>Two blog posts in the last 24 hours caught my attention. First was this post by Jeff Leek noting that there are many fields which are applied statistics by another name (and I&amp;rsquo;d add operations research to his list). The second is an excellent post on Cloudera&amp;rsquo;s blog on constructing case-control studies. It is generally excellent, but has this rather unfortunate (in my view) statement:
Analyzing a case-control study is a problem for a statistician.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>